<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-21T00:06:06+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Shahid Hussain | Blog</title><subtitle>A Data Science and Mathematics blog, focusing on Machine learning algorithms.</subtitle><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Dimension Reduction Methods</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/identifying-when-to-use-pca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dimension Reduction Methods" /><published>2024-06-12T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/identifying-when-to-use-pca</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/identifying-when-to-use-pca/">&lt;p&gt;Main Ones to cover : LLE LTSA Isomap MDS Spectral embedding t-SNE 
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqtNjwI60dQ&amp;amp;list=PLPrxGIUWsqP3MNmrqbarg-FbMW88_fzsp&amp;amp;index=6
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqtNjwI60dQ&amp;amp;list=PLPrxGIUWsqP3MNmrqbarg-FbMW88_fzsp&amp;amp;index=6
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Zk2UFGIrd0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today i was learning about Spectral decomposition and the implciation leading to Spectral Value Decompositon, and as many of you guys know the important role SVD plays to Priciple component anlysis, but then the question arise, I want to use PCA but when should I?
The following notes are from “Introduction to Dimensionality Reduction - Presentation at WangLab in the University of Toronto”. What i will try to do is outline the main methodologies used in dimension reductionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-manifold&quot;&gt;What is a Manifold?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;When we work with data we have many attributes to describe a certain event we combine all the into  a feature vector $ X = [x_1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x_2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x_3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x_n] $ . Suppose we have a table describing people then each column can be age, income, location etc. so $ x_i $ represent columns which we combina into a column vector.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if the only have less then 3 attribute then we can graph these attributes. Majority of the time given there is not major noise in a data, that is error in sample, data naturally stay close to one another, this is known as the Manifold Hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/manifolds/manifold_types.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Manifold-types&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two many types of ways data can lay in a low dimensional space, (a) subspace : which is hyperplane  in, subspace are importantly always linear OR  (b) submanifold, which is like a squiskly hyperplane, but importantly, locally linear, that is, if we zoom in very close into the submanifold it would seem we were in a flat plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a submanifold is a smooth continous function, as it allows use to use calculus. Before we cover the identify submanifold we need to cover the types of dimentionaliy reductions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;types-of-reduction-dimensionality&quot;&gt;Types of Reduction Dimensionality&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally Reduct of Dimension can be placed into three categories&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/manifolds/type_of_dimension_reductionality.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Type-reduction-methods&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spectral-dimentional-reductionaly&quot;&gt;Spectral Dimentional Reductionaly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There dimension method take a geometric approach, an a Example PCA, which uses the Coaraicne Matrix to computre eigenvalues and eigenvector. Now Since eigenvalues are the length of eigenvectors, then this can be used to identify the varaicne of a singualr feature (age). 
The problem then arrises since PCA uses eigenvalues and vector what happens if the data is in a submanifold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/manifolds/spectral_decomposition.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spectral-methods&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;clearly from (a) consdier the Green and red dots if we use PCA, the eigenvalue would be small, indicating small variacne, even though that data really sits on a submanifold,thus would lead to a underfitting model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So by idenfitying our data is in a submanifold, we we properly reduced the dimenstion by flatting out the submanifold and then reducing the size of the space, which would over underfitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;probabilistic-dimension-reductionaliy&quot;&gt;Probabilistic Dimension Reductionaliy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name suggest, this take a probalisitc approach to dimention reductionaly, which includes Probabilistic Principal Component Analysis (PPCA), SNE, T-SNE, UMAP and random projection, factor analysis and SDR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Projects" /><summary type="html">Main Ones to cover : LLE LTSA Isomap MDS Spectral embedding t-SNE https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqtNjwI60dQ&amp;amp;list=PLPrxGIUWsqP3MNmrqbarg-FbMW88_fzsp&amp;amp;index=6 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqtNjwI60dQ&amp;amp;list=PLPrxGIUWsqP3MNmrqbarg-FbMW88_fzsp&amp;amp;index=6 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Zk2UFGIrd0</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Episode Two UNSW Data Soc x IBM ML project : From Raw to EDA</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/episdoe-two-datasoc-ibm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Episode Two UNSW Data Soc x IBM ML project : From Raw to EDA" /><published>2024-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/episdoe-two-datasoc-ibm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/episdoe-two-datasoc-ibm/">&lt;p&gt;Today was the first lecutre from Dr. Saeed Kasmani, a Senior AI engineer from IBM and the agenda was explroing 
EDA, Data cleaning &amp;amp; profiling, Assessing data quality, Data rejection &amp;amp; imputation, Exploring &amp;amp; visualising 
categorical/continuous data and Feature Engineering&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-science-flowchart&quot;&gt;Data Science flowchart&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-making-data-usable&quot;&gt;1. Making data Usable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the first steps of making raw data usuable is under 4 terms data wranlgeing, profialig, cleanring and munging. 
In data wrangle the goals is to is fix critical issuess, including sourcing, laoding and preclearning the data. 
Data profiling and cleaning main goals is to understand the essential characterisic of the data, thoruhg aplpying transformation of features and implemeting strategies for missing data and invlid data. 
Lastly data muging is reshapding data to perform anaysis (Exploratory data analysis)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-explroatory-data-analysis&quot;&gt;2. Explroatory data analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An approach of analyzing data sets to summarize their main characteristics, through data visualisation or statisitcal graphs, with the main goal of is it a useful proxy for our learning model, client objective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-developing-anlaystics-and-models-to-adresss-our-original-problem&quot;&gt;3. Developing anlaystics and models to adresss our original problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the stage we use different stratistical learning algorithms create deicsion boundaries, either thoruhg parametric or non-parametric methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;exploring-data-wrangling&quot;&gt;Exploring Data Wrangling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is a referenced using ‘Principles of Data Wrangling: Practical Techniques for Data Preparation’ by Tye Rattenbury, Connor Carreras, Sean Kandel, Joseph M. Hellerstein, Jeffrey Heer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;role-of-data-preposing&quot;&gt;Role of data preposing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the authors, data scientist spend 50 - 80 % of there times on data preproccessing and EDA rather then statistical learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;obtaining-the-magic-threshold&quot;&gt;Obtaining the MAgic threshold&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given we want to a social media company wants to grow as a core objective, the analytics team main objective is to create a magic threshold which (1) has a concise KPI target thats predicts the objective (2) is actionable. Example ‘key predictor of new engagement is new users tshould conenct 10 friedns within 14 days’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-stages&quot;&gt;Data stages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three mains stages of data preproccessing including (1) Raw stage (2)Refined Stage and (3) Production stage each stage has its own&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Projects" /><summary type="html">Today was the first lecutre from Dr. Saeed Kasmani, a Senior AI engineer from IBM and the agenda was explroing EDA, Data cleaning &amp;amp; profiling, Assessing data quality, Data rejection &amp;amp; imputation, Exploring &amp;amp; visualising categorical/continuous data and Feature Engineering</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Episode One (UNSW Data Soc x IBM ML project) : Data Preproccessing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/episode-one-data-scoc-ibm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Episode One (UNSW Data Soc x IBM ML project) : Data Preproccessing" /><published>2024-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/episode-one-data-scoc-ibm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/episode-one-data-scoc-ibm/">&lt;p&gt;Today was the first day of attending a term-long project with Data Society UNSW, in collaboration with IBM. The main premise is that throughout the term, we will try to optimize a machine learning algorithm with a dataset. During the term, an IBM machine learning engineer will teach us the fundamentals of machine learning, including data preprocessing and learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-client-and-objective&quot;&gt;The client and objective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your client is a multinational real estate developer that builds residential and commercial properties 
around the world. They have a large portfolio of projects that are in development simultaneously. They 
currently have a 25% failure rate for their projects that is significantly higher than the industry 
benchmark of less than 10%. They would like to understand what the key leading indicators for project 
failure are when they are planning their projects. This will allow them to only invest capital into the best 
quality projects. They also want to know ongoing which projects are likely to fail so they can cut their 
losses and cease the projects. Secondly, the real estate developer would like to search local building 
policies to quickly find the relevant answers as they plan their developments. This could include zoning 
policies, environmental policies and development planning policies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;break-down-the-client-objective&quot;&gt;Break down the client objective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve picking projects - find the likelihood of project failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduced speed to policy search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-project-overview&quot;&gt;Weekly project Overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ibm/ibm-weekly-break.png&quot; alt=&quot;weeklyoverview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-preprocessing&quot;&gt;Data preprocessing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our main objective before making any inference of learning models is to understand the fundamental question&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-our-data-useful-proxy-for-understanding-our-problem&quot;&gt;Does our data useful ‘proxy’ for understanding our problem?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is known as exploratory data analysis, for which is a process done after the data is usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-usable-data&quot;&gt;What is usable data?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a usable dataset is the process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Wrangling - sourcing, loading, and precleaning the 
data so we can see what it really looks like, fixing critical issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data profiling and cleaning - understanding the essential characteristics of the data , applying preliminary transformations to  confer context and meaning. Continuing implementing strategies for missing and invalid data (Imputations methods)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data mugging - reshaping data to prepare it for analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important lesson is that this is not a linear cycle, from Data Wrangling to Data mugging to learning models. It a iterative process for which we will continuously revise our data to import our analysis and learning model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ibm/IBM_data_cleaning_fixing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;data-cleaning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-go-about-data-cleaning-and-profiling&quot;&gt;How to go about Data Cleaning and Profiling?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After conducting basic data wrangling, you would proceed to preliminary data cleaning, including reformatting, data type conversion, and dealing with dirty data. Secondly, basic data profiling includes finding data types, data ranges (continuous), and categories. Thirdly, one of the most important parts of this stage is ‘assessing data quality’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When assessing data quality, we look at accuracy, reliability (veracity), currency, and relevance. This covers how many invalid or missing values each feature, row, or the overall dataset has, and what the effect is of throwing out or imputing the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, in learning algorithms, we assume each sample (i.e., each row) is part of some unknown distribution. That is to say, even the samples that are missing play a part. Therefore, by removing or imputing samples, we risk changing the distribution of the training set, which can result in large test errors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;visualizing-data&quot;&gt;Visualizing Data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this process is done, we are now ready to explore our data visually. Through this process, we can identify skewness, the mean, and even outliers. Graphs include scatterplots, wireframe plots, surface plots, histograms, box-whisker plots, and heat maps. After all these processes, we finally begin to understand the data and the features of each column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-steps-before-trying-a-learning-model&quot;&gt;Final steps before trying a learning model&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yay, we are on our last step before the big one: ML algorithms! So now all data is cleaned, we have a solid grasp of the data, and we need to select which data helps us the most in categorizing/predicting our label. This involves three steps: feature engineering, feature reduction, and feature selection!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feature engineering in machine learning involves extracting useful features from the given input data, considering the target to be learned and the machine learning model used. It involves transforming data into forms that better relate to the underlying target to be learned. This includes variable transformations such as square root and Box-Cox transformations, and categorical encoding, like one-hot encoding in sk-learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feature reduction and selection involve reducing the number of variables. This is more commonly done under unsupervised learning using techniques such as PCA, factor analysis, and t-SNE. Amazingly, sk-learn has a whole user guide on feature selection!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there we have it! Now, we know the basic outline of data preprocessing. Just a little note: finding valuable, straight-to-the-point information on data preprocessing is extremely difficult. Some textbooks cover the basics, while others go too in-depth. There isn’t anything that’s just enough to perform a basic data science project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Projects" /><summary type="html">Today was the first day of attending a term-long project with Data Society UNSW, in collaboration with IBM. The main premise is that throughout the term, we will try to optimize a machine learning algorithm with a dataset. During the term, an IBM machine learning engineer will teach us the fundamentals of machine learning, including data preprocessing and learning algorithms.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Confidence Intervals vs Credible Intervals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stats/Confidence-Intervals-Credible-Intervals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Confidence Intervals vs Credible Intervals" /><published>2024-05-29T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stats/Confidence-Intervals-Credible-Intervals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stats/Confidence-Intervals-Credible-Intervals/"></content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Stats" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bayesian statistics vs frequentist statistics : Estimating Probability From Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ml/Estimate-Probability-from-data/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bayesian statistics vs frequentist statistics : Estimating Probability From Data" /><published>2024-05-21T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-21T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ml/Estimate-Probability-from-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ml/Estimate-Probability-from-data/">&lt;p&gt;Today I was watching Kilian Weinberger lecture on Estimating Probabilities from Data: Maximum Likelihood Estimation” Cornell CS4780 SP17 and now I finally understand the difference between the types of statistics (Also I read “Probabilistic Machine Learning: An Introduction” by Kevin Murphy). The following post will discuss the difference between the two most common schools of statistics, through the lens of machine learning, data estimation using probaiblity; MLE and MAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;recall&quot;&gt;Recall&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;An important part of why machine can learning is that we assume that all samples points taken are from the same distribution, $ (x_i, y_i) ~ P, \forall i \in \mathbb{Z}^{+} $ and are i.i.d. Now using this assumption which is the backbone of all learning algorithms, then there $ \exists P(x,y) $, for which a conditional expectation can also be calculated, $ P(y&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x) $, that is, given a feature what the the probability that it lands on this specific label. Alternatively , $ P(x&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;y) $ must also exist, that is given a label what is the probability that it displays certain features. The study of both conditional probabilities are separated using Bayes Theorem,&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    P(x | y) &amp;amp;\propto P(y | x)P(x) \quad\quad\text{Discriminative Learning} \\ 
    P(y | x) &amp;amp;\propto P(x | y)P(y) \quad\quad\text{Generative Learning}
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;In essence, discriminative learning aims to create explicit boundaries between classes of labels, similar to SVMs, Perceptron, and k-NN. On the other hand, generative learning tries to model the distribution of individual classes, such as Naive Bayes or Gaussian Mixture Models (GMM). Within each of these types of learning, you can have parametric models, where we assume the distribution of ( p(x,y) ) comes from a certain well-known distribution like normal, Bernoulli, exponential, or non-parametric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-parameter&quot;&gt;What is a parameter?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;given some distribution a parameter is a point estimate that characteristics a known class of distribution. I’m sure you have heard of common well know distribution including $N(\mu, \sigma^2)$ or $ \mathrm{Bern}(\lambda)$. In this case $\theta$, our parameter can be a set, or singular point estimate which character our distribution so $\theta = (\sigma^2, \mu)$ or $\theta = (\lambda) $&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivating-example&quot;&gt;Motivating example&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a motivating exmaples consdier flipped a equally wieghted coin. Say we coin and we get \(D = \{ T , T, T, H, H, H, H, T, T, T, T \}\). Now considering it is eually wieghted coin we would hope that our probbilities of getting each side of the dice as \(\frac{1}{2}\) something from pervious years we have come to know. Say we want to know what is the probaiblites of getting a head, then the most intuitive method would be to&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation*}
    P(\text{getting heads}) = \frac{n_h}{n_t + n_h}
\end{equation*}\]

&lt;p&gt;where $ \text{n} = \text{Number of times gotten a side}$ . Yet it used this equation for our set of outcomes $ D $, we find $ P(\text{heads}) = \frac{4}{11} $, which isn’t 50 \% as we expected. Why is that did we not find the right probability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;frequentist-vs-bayesian-n-perspective&quot;&gt;Frequentist vs Bayesian n Perspective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;When studying probability theory, we are concerned with $ p(D&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;\theta) $, which models the distribution with some known $ \theta $. On the other hand, in statistics, previously known as inverse probability theory, we are given some data, and we aim to infer the unknown parameters $ \theta $ given observations, $ p(\theta&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;D) $.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, Frequentist are concerned with ‘frequency’, meaning that over time, the asymptotic behavior of our probability will converge to a certain number, as in the example above. Importantly, this requires a lot of data; otherwise, we would be overfitting. On the other hand, Bayesian statisticians know that data is readily available, and indeed, we have some assumptions we know about the data. Thus, they assume some ‘prior’ distribution of $p(\theta)$ from expertise, enabling them to readily use it when a small sample size is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;frequentist-mle&quot;&gt;Frequentist: MLE&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we define&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
p(\mathcal{D}|\theta) = \prod_{n=1}^N p(y_n|x_n, \theta)
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;that is our i.i.d assumption of machine learning. Then applying a log (we use to simply computation), we get the log-likelihood,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
\mathcal{L}(\theta) = \sum_{n=1}^N log( p(y_n|x_n, \theta)).
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;So, then we define MLE of a parameter&lt;/p&gt;

\[\hat{\theta}_{MLE} = \arg\max_{\theta} \sum_{n=1}^N \log p(y_n | x_n, \theta)\]

&lt;p&gt;So optimisations theory is easier, to optimise a function through minimize cost functions so,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\theta_{\text{MLE}}^{\hat{}} = \arg\max_{\theta} - \sum_{n=1}^N \log p(y_n | x_n, \theta)\]

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mle-example&quot;&gt;MLE example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to our examples we flips coins, we now can assume that $p(x,y) ~ Bern(\lambda) $, where now $\theta = P(Y = 1) $, where $Y = number of times of getting heads heads$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \mathcal{L}(\theta) = \arg\max_{\theta} - \left( \sum_{n=1}^N \mathbb{1}_{y_n=1} \log(\theta) + \mathbb{1}_{y_n=0} \log(1 - \theta) \right).
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Let, $ N1 = \sum_{n=1}^N \mathbb{1}&lt;em&gt;{y_n=1}$ and $ N0 =  sum&lt;/em&gt;{n=1}^N \mathbb{1}&lt;em&gt;{y_n=0} $. Now, we can use differentiating and let the loss function equal 0 to find the minimum (like in high school finding the minimum point of a function) to find $\hat{\theta}&lt;/em&gt;{MLE}$,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \hat{\theta}_{MLE}= \frac{N1}{N0 + N1}
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this similar to our intuition right? This is known as classical statistics, or Frequentist statistics. Importantly we done assume  $\theta$ has any distribution itself but rather is a parameter which contains information about the distribution of a data points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-we-didnt-get-any-heads-in-out-sample&quot;&gt;What is we didnt get any heads in out sample?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;he $ \hat{\theta}_{MLE} = 0 $. Is this correct? Well, of course not. We know from our intuition it should be $ \frac{1}{2} $. So Frequentists use this method, knowing we (plus one) Laplace Smoothing to ensure in the case of our sample not having an event occurring,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation*}
\hat{\theta}_{MLE}= \frac{N1 + 1 }{N0 + N1 + 2}
\end{equation*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Since there is only two classes in our examples head or tails so we add 2 in the denominator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;map&quot;&gt;MAP&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively in Bayesian statistics we don’t consider Laplace smoothing or $\theta$ as just a parameter but rather in build upon the notion that we don’t have allot of data and data can’t always model the distribution of the sample accurately. So we make this assumption (adding bias) that $ \theta $ random variable. Now a random variable is neither a variables or random but rather a function which maps points of a measurable set $ \sigma$-algebra to the real number line, but a important property is that random variables can have distributions. So, now we can express to new equations, using Bayes Theorem,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
P(\theta | D) &amp;amp;= \frac{P(D | \theta) P(\theta)}{ P(D)} \Rightarrow \\ 
P(\theta | D) &amp;amp;\quad\propto\quad P(D | \theta) P(\theta). \\ 
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Now in Bayesian Statistics, each component is named,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;$ P(D&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;\theta) $ Likelihood of data given ( \theta )&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;$ P(\theta&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;D)$ (posterior distribution): Distribution over the parameter(s) ( \theta ) after we have observed the data&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$P(\theta) $ (prior): Distribution over the parameter(s) ( \theta ) before we see any data. 
We need to choose the prior distribution using our expertise and knowledge which of course can work out great, or horribly wrong if we assume the distribution of our prior wrong. So now,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
     p(\mathcal{D}|\theta) &amp;amp;= \prod_{n=1}^N p(y_n|x_n, \theta)p(\theta) \\
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Applying log,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \mathcal{L}(\theta)&amp;amp;= \sum_{n=1}^N log(p(y_n|x_n, \theta))+ \sum_{n=1}^N log( p(\theta)) \\
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;So,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \hat{\theta}_{map} = \arg\max_{\theta} \mathcal{L}(\theta)
\end{align*}\]

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Going back to the coin flip we can assume our prior distribution (guess) is $  p(\theta) = Beta(\theta&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;a, b) $ then our log likelihood ends up becoming&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \mathcal{L}(\theta) = &amp;amp;\left( \sum_{n=1}^N \mathbb{1}_{y_n=1} \log(\theta) + \mathbb{1}_{y_n=0} \log(1 - \theta) \right) + [(a - 1)log(\theta) + (b - 1)log(1 - \theta)]
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;Then using normal minimisation method of finding first derivative letting it equal to zero to find minimizer for $\hat{\theta})$ we get&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align*}
    \hat{\theta}_{map} = \frac{N1 + a - 1}{N1 + N0 + a + b - 2}
\end{align*}\]

&lt;p&gt;So by assuming a prior distribution in Bayesian statistics we end up getting a very similar estimator found in Frequentist statistics using Laplace Smoothing. So in a sense they are very similar!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="ML" /><summary type="html">Today I was watching Kilian Weinberger lecture on Estimating Probabilities from Data: Maximum Likelihood Estimation” Cornell CS4780 SP17 and now I finally understand the difference between the types of statistics (Also I read “Probabilistic Machine Learning: An Introduction” by Kevin Murphy). The following post will discuss the difference between the two most common schools of statistics, through the lens of machine learning, data estimation using probaiblity; MLE and MAP.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Weak Strong Law Large Numbers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/weak-strong-law-large-numbers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weak Strong Law Large Numbers" /><published>2024-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/weak-strong-law-large-numbers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/weak-strong-law-large-numbers/"></content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How sampling distribution is the link between Machine Learning and data science</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/random/distribution-link-datascience-ml/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How sampling distribution is the link between Machine Learning and data science" /><published>2024-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/random/distribution-link-datascience-ml</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/random/distribution-link-datascience-ml/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;ever-wondered-how-these-two-field-like-with-concrete-examples&quot;&gt;Ever wondered how these two field like with concrete examples?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data science formull is defined “statistics, scientific computing, scientific methods, processes, algorithms and systems to extract or extrapolate knowledge and insights from potentially noisy, structured, or unstructured data”. In a informal sense we are trying to transform raw data into strucutre data for a specific task. Now this take can range from mere simple data analysis to more complex task including classifying data or regression problems. Now, one role of data sciecne is to provide data to machine learning engineers for a spcifci learning problem.  So the next question begins ‘what does the macvhien learnign requires from a data scientist to ensrue data is correct?’. We will look at the basics of machine learning algorithsm, including loss functions, assumptions and then devlve into the importance of data quality given by data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;little-about-machine-learning&quot;&gt;Little about machine learning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is a process where by a machine, usually a program, learns from given data where by we have input, \(X\) and output \(Y\), known as feature inputs and labels, respectively. Now the goals is to create a program which can adequatly be able to given predict ‘label’ given a new input. An exmaples can be classify females and males, know a data scientist will go out and take picture of males and females, and then label them both males or female, then this is given to a machine leanring program for which is looks at data and tries to understand distinction bewteen male and females, untill it get very good at it. Then we will given it new picture and then hopefully it will be able to identify correctly geneder of the male or female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;now-an-important-assumptio-we-make-is-machine-learning-is-that-all-samples-take-have-the-same-distribtion-p-and-are-iid-why&quot;&gt;Now an important assumptio we make is Machine learning is that all samples take have the same distribtion \(P\) and are i.i.d why?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates the link between machien learning and data sciecne. Ifall possible data that we can be given is from the same distribition, since if they it would be impossible to predict or classify random selected people since we a any random input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example--gender-shades-project-2018&quot;&gt;Example : Gender Shades project 2018&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018 gender classification algorithms developed by IBM and Microsoft was studye based on miclassification based upon skin tone, from four cateogires: darker-skinned females, darker-skinned males, lighter-skinned females, and lighter-skinned males. All three algorithms performed the worst on darker-skinned females, with error rates up to 34% higher than for lighter-skinned males.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key reaosn might be the samples distribution, now say the task to recognise face, if a data scientist provides face of only light-skinned males then cleary the algorithsm will only be able to identify these indviduals and fall short on other skins tones. So the distribution we wrong for the task since the data that the algorith was trained was different to the actually dsitirbution it was testet on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;continying&quot;&gt;Continying&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionaly, these samples must be i.i.d, so we have already adressed the identifcallty distribution, but indepecne is importance is to ensure that these samples done effect one another cause if they do it would be impossible to find the relationship between two samples (x_i, y_i)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-a-machine-algorithm-works-using-out-asusmption&quot;&gt;How a Machine algorithm works using out asusmption&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So currently I’ve talked about the assumption that all possible data that an algorithsm will very see is given by data sciecntist so the roels of trhe data sciecne to provides data which will represent all possible data it will be given in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-then-does-a-machine-learning-engineer-optimise-this-data&quot;&gt;How then does a Machine learning engineer optimise this data?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(add picture)
so out goals to minimise the error rates of our algorithm chosen h, we do this through choose a loss function which is appropriate to the task, now importantly iv talked about teh improtance of the algorithm bening able to generalise to any data set and that the data, of course  is assumpted to from the same distribution \(P\). Our easier first guess is for out loos function&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;l(h;D)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but the key problem is that this only optimsised out dataset in a sense it memories out data givne but give new sample it would not be able to rpedict it well, so we must create a denfition which generlaise well for all possible data from a asusmed distirbution 
\(E(l(X,Y))_{(x_i,y_i) ~ P}\)
That is we want to find the middle weight of all possible samples from data future and past&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-we-we-implement-this-into-our-machine-leanring-program&quot;&gt;How we we implement this into our machine leanring program?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we split data into test and training set, for the sole reason is that out assumption is all points are (xi,yi) ~ P so we act like our data is a represnetaiotn of the whole population of task we need to learn and for that reason we only touch our test set for final evaluation process. we it would givne use a interpretation of how well&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conlusion&quot;&gt;Conlusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the reaosn why data sciecne is importacne of machine learning engineers is that since machine leanirng engineeers assume that all data for a learnign as has the same distribution, the data scienctist roles is to ensure that the data they provides represent all possible inputs for that task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Random" /><summary type="html">Ever wondered how these two field like with concrete examples? Data science formull is defined “statistics, scientific computing, scientific methods, processes, algorithms and systems to extract or extrapolate knowledge and insights from potentially noisy, structured, or unstructured data”. In a informal sense we are trying to transform raw data into strucutre data for a specific task. Now this take can range from mere simple data analysis to more complex task including classifying data or regression problems. Now, one role of data sciecne is to provide data to machine learning engineers for a spcifci learning problem. So the next question begins ‘what does the macvhien learnign requires from a data scientist to ensrue data is correct?’. We will look at the basics of machine learning algorithsm, including loss functions, assumptions and then devlve into the importance of data quality given by data scientist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I went from 40 WPM to 100 WPM in 3 months without trying!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/random/improving-typing-speed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I went from 40 WPM to 100 WPM in 3 months without trying!" /><published>2024-05-17T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-17T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/random/improving-typing-speed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/random/improving-typing-speed/">&lt;p&gt;Flashbacks to high school when all my friends used to engage in typing test battles; touch typing, speed, the whole shebang. Then there was me, trying to look at the keyboard, using two fingers from each hand, and managing a grand total of 40 WPM. HUMPH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve begun to understand the importance of being able to type fast and its perks. Not only does it help with completing computer tasks faster, but as technology natives, it’s almost a necessity. More importantly, I believe in having mastery over all parts of my body! I feel there’s some hidden neurological benefits in being able to control your fingers eloquently; it helps in learning other skills faster. From my observations, people who type fast usually pick up instruments a lot quicker compared to myself; trying to learn guitar was extremely difficult!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a quick rundown of how I improved my typing speed without really following any formal tutorials:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tip-1-passive-learning-using-monkeytype&quot;&gt;Tip 1: Passive learning using MonkeyType&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice until mastery. I pretty much just spammed 25-second MonkeyType tests; it’s so easy and doesn’t take much time. Every time you’re about to start a new task, just hop on and smash out a test. Not only does Huberman always say we learn best if we stop thinking for like 10-15 seconds, but it’s also kinda fun trying to beat a previous score like it’s a video game. (I’ve done 400 test already! )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tip-2-start-from-basics-using-at-least-four-fingers&quot;&gt;Tip 2: Start from basics, using at least four fingers!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, this is a tough one, but if you’re currently only using two fingers, you have to move to using four fingers; your learning curve will be exponential. In the beginning, it will be difficult, but as you get used to it, the rate of learning will be insane!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tip-3-dont-look-at-the-keyboard&quot;&gt;Tip 3: Don’t look at the keyboard&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As computer natives, even though we think we don’t know where the keys are, we subconsciously already know where all the letters are on the keyboard; we just need to practice a little!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as that!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Random" /><summary type="html">Flashbacks to high school when all my friends used to engage in typing test battles; touch typing, speed, the whole shebang. Then there was me, trying to look at the keyboard, using two fingers from each hand, and managing a grand total of 40 WPM. HUMPH.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bias-variance tradeoff vs approximation-estimation tradeoff</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/statistics/tradeoffs-methods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bias-variance tradeoff vs approximation-estimation tradeoff" /><published>2024-05-15T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/statistics/tradeoffs-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/statistics/tradeoffs-methods/">&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been reading a textbook called ‘Data Science and Machine Learning Mathematical and Statistical Methods’ by a previous professor Zdravko I. Botev and i came across an interesting nation ‘approximation-estimation tradeoff’. Uptil now I, like most people was only aware of bias-variacne tradeoff being the most common problem with optimsing mahcine learning algorithms. So the aim of this post of to classify the difference between the two using the aid of a provious textbook and a the article ‘Bias/Variancer is not the same as Approimation/Estimation’ by Gavin brown and Riccardo Ali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;adressing-perspectives&quot;&gt;Adressing Perspective’s&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are aware that machine learning and data sciecne originated from the field of Statistics and Mathematics, yet many course taught focus on using training data to optimsatie machine learning algorithsm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the importanat distinction is ‘approximation-estimation tradeoff was published first and orignates from Statistical learning theory, which focuses on a excess risk in mathematical defintiion (Bayes model), yet bias-variacne trade off focuses on a defintion akin to protical, focusing on the problem risk when using training data for trainfed models, more akin to the problems faced practically in the industry today’&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><summary type="html">Recently I’ve been reading a textbook called ‘Data Science and Machine Learning Mathematical and Statistical Methods’ by a previous professor Zdravko I. Botev and i came across an interesting nation ‘approximation-estimation tradeoff’. Uptil now I, like most people was only aware of bias-variacne tradeoff being the most common problem with optimsing mahcine learning algorithms. So the aim of this post of to classify the difference between the two using the aid of a provious textbook and a the article ‘Bias/Variancer is not the same as Approimation/Estimation’ by Gavin brown and Riccardo Ali.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Statistical Learning Theory Episode One ‘Building the foundation’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/statistics/Overview-of-staticial-theory-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Statistical Learning Theory Episode One ‘Building the foundation’" /><published>2024-05-15T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/statistics/Overview-of-staticial-theory-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/statistics/Overview-of-staticial-theory-learning/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’v been currently learning about staticial learning theory to gain a mathematical udnertsanding of machine learning. So today the first part of a few psot focusing in undertsanding statistical learning theory. This first post is based on ‘Complete Statistical Theory of Learning (Vladimir Vapnik) | MIT Deep Learning Series’. Lets get into it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-do-we-care-about-statistical-learning-theory&quot;&gt;Why do we care about statistical learning theory?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical learnign theory predates today machie learing algorithsm. Originating from Russia in the 1960’s, the key goals was to formualting ‘learning’ through data. Machine learing algorithm take example training data then it infers ‘general ruels’ which can both answer a its label and over time after many samples can generalised to unseen examples known as inductive reasoning/inferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This domain of study lead to the now famous algorithsm known as Support Vector Machines which is now a staple of patter recognition.To enable this learning process statistician devleoped a framework to formuale this process; regression, classification, clustering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;framework-of-staitsitcal-learning-theory&quot;&gt;Framework of staitsitcal learning theory&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General SLT attems to answer 4 main questions;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which learning tasks can be performed by computers in general (positive and negative results)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What kind of assumptions do we have to make such that machine learning can be successful a.k.a inductive bias? (Turns out this is inevitable for a sucessfull learning algorithsm “No Free-Lunch Theorem”!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the key properties a learning algorithm needs to satisfy in order to be successful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which performance guarantees can we give on the results of certain learning algorithms? - this ones important we want to ensure our mechanism learns the right outcome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;types-of-learning&quot;&gt;Types of learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be focusing on explanation through the leaner-teacher model, in which the learning is the algorithm, the environment is the training data and the teacher guides the experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supervised vs unsupervised learning : the learner interects with the environment in suprervised learning the leaners “uses experiences from environment to gain expertise” in which a teacher provides the experiecnes (training data) and then “apply” its experiecnes to new data given by the teacher (test data). However, in unserpvised learning the teacher provides ‘experiences’ to the learner (training data), and the leaner aims to ‘summerise’ the experiences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Active vs Passive : If the learner interects with the enviuronement provided by the teacher (training data) and gives the teacher quiries about the experiecnes then is is an acitvie leaner, else if it doesnt inquire about the experiences and merlery just take the experiecnes in then its is passive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals is the teacher naturlally is to provide the best informatio for the leaner to understand the taks as quickly as possible, but course how the teacher learner the task itself is unknown so we assume it is random process. An alternative is adversiary teacher, who pruposefuly provides bad information to see if the leaner undertsanding the experinces, usualyl used in worst-case scienario’s!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;formulising-the-learning-equation&quot;&gt;Formulising the learning equation&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Statistics" /><summary type="html">Overview I’v been currently learning about staticial learning theory to gain a mathematical udnertsanding of machine learning. So today the first part of a few psot focusing in undertsanding statistical learning theory. This first post is based on ‘Complete Statistical Theory of Learning (Vladimir Vapnik) | MIT Deep Learning Series’. Lets get into it!</summary></entry></feed>