<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-17T19:11:09+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Shahid Hussain | Blog</title><subtitle>A Data Science and Mathematics blog, focusing on Machine learning algorithms.</subtitle><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">My First Post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/miscellaneous/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Post" /><published>2023-12-15T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2023-12-15T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/miscellaneous/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Shahid0120.github.io/miscellaneous/first-post/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;welcome-to-my-blog&quot;&gt;Welcome to My Blog!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome! This is my very first post on my new blog, and I’m thrilled to share my journey of exploration and information-sharing with fellow students like myself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;most-important-question-first-so-how-did-i-get-into-machine-learning&quot;&gt;Most important question first, so how did I get into Machine Learning?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve always been interested in self-improvement. This interest started at a young age, focusing not only on becoming more effective in my studies but also on optimizing my mental and physical well-being. I regularly listen to inspiring figures like Andrew Huberman, Lex Friedman, and many more. More specifically, my journey into Machine Learning began when I took a course at UNSW called “Digital and Web Analytics.” One of the assessment tasks was to perform a sentiment analysis on a crisis a company had gone through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially confused about what “sentiment analysis” entailed, I started exploring scientific papers, attending random lectures, and kept encountering the term “Machine Learning.” Somehow, I created a sentiment analysis of public opinion on whether comments on YouTube and Twitter were positive, negative, or neutral using Natural Language Processing. I coded, but I faced one big problem—I had no idea how the sentiment analysis packages worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, while navigating this, I was concurrently enrolled in a course on “Linear Models,” delving into topics like linear regression, which significantly sparked my interest. Unfortunately, the lectures never explained anything about what Machine Learning is! Why! Fueled by motivation to learn how exactly a machine categorizes words and wha alternative are there to linear regression, I scoured the internet to learn more, eventually leading me to discover the vast world of Machine Learning! And that’s the current journey I’m on now, and I can’t wait to learn more!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shahid Hussain</name><email>shahid.hussain0120@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Miscellaneous" /><summary type="html">Welcome to My Blog!</summary></entry></feed>